<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lif of Saincte Katheryne</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1505</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4813.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21566760</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21566760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24816</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18176)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24816)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1726:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lif of Saincte Katheryne</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8]+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Pynson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1505?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Illustrated t.p.</note>
                  <note>Publisher and date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Fragment consisting of signatures A2, A3, A6, A7.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catherine, --  of Alexandria, Saint.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="life_of_St.Catherine_of_Alexandria">
            <pb facs="tcp:24816:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 148 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>The lif of ſaincte katheryne</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of St. Catherine of Alexandria</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:24816:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 149 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:24816:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 149 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:24816:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 150 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:24816:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 150 -->
            <head>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere begynneth the ryghte excellent and full gloryous lyfe and paſſyon of the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte blyſſed virgyn and martyr ſaynte Katheryne.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The fyrſt chaptre.</head>
               <p>THis blyſſed virgyn ſaynt katheryn was by the dyſcent of the lyne and of the noble kyn rede of the Emperoure of Rome / as it ſhalle be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared more playnly here after / by a noble cronycle whiche mooſt blyſſed lyfe and conuerſacyon was write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne doctour Athanaſiꝰ that knew hir byrth hir kynred hir holy lyfe &amp; conuerſacyon. And this ſame Athanaſius was done of hir may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in hir tender age / and by the grace of the holy goſt ſhe was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to the faithe. And after that ſhe was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted / ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted the ſame athanaſi us by holy and meruelous werkes that oure lorde wrought in hir. and after by his wyſdom he was made biſſhop of Aliſandre / &amp; was a glorious pyler of holy church / by the grace of oure lorde god &amp; hir holy meritis / as we do fynde by credible cronycles For in the tyme of themperour Diocleſian &amp; maxi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mian / ſo great &amp; cruel tyranny was ſhewed in the worlde &amp; not only of criſten but alſo of paynymes that in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme many a realme that was ſub get to tome put a way the yok of ther ſeruage &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled aienſt them perour amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge which the realme of Ermony was one of the mooſte that myghtely
<pb facs="tcp:24816:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 151 -->
                  <pb facs="tcp:24816:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 151 -->withſtode the tribute that longed to the emperour of rome wherfore ther was choſen to apeas that re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bellyon a lorde of greate dygnyte of the counſeyle of highe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancius which was afore al other man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in armes / and therwith right diſcrete and fulle of vertues. The which lorde than whanne he cam in to Ermony ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched ſo by hys vertue and man lye gouernaunce that rebellyon / that he deſerued the loue of all his ennemyes / ſoo ferfurthe / that the kynge and alle his people deſyred that he ſhulde wedde the doughter and the heire of the lande and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne this was doone within a whyle after the kynge of Ermonie dyed / &amp; conſtancius was crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned kynge of that lande the which within a while after had a ſon by the quene the which was clepid coſtus And ſone after that died the quene for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was made great lamentacion of hir people. After whos dethe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancius the kynge tourned agayne to Rome for to ſe the emperoures welfare / and for to ſe &amp; knowe howe his lordeſhyppes were gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in tho partyes. and in the mene tyme came ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges to themperour of Rome howe that greate brytayne that nowe is called Englonde rebellyd agaynſte the emperour of Rome. wherefore it was ſene amonge the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel / that it was to requyre con ſtanciꝰ the kyng of Ermonie to take on hym for to redreſſe that rebellyon. the which requeſt he godlly graunted &amp; drew him towardes tho ꝑties &amp; in hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge he ruled hym ſo by his vertue &amp; prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:24816:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 152 -->
                  <pb facs="tcp:24816:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 152 -->wherefore we be in derkenes &amp; tyl the light of grac<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come we may not ſe the clere waye. and whanne hym lyſt to come he ſhal voyde away the derk clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of ignorance. &amp; ſhe we hym clerely to me whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I ſo ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly deſyre and loue. And if ſo be that hym lyſte not that I fynde hym / yet reaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth me to kepe hole that is vnhurt. wherfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re I beſeche you humbly my lady my moder that ye ne noone other neuer meue moore of this mater For I by hyghte you playnely that for to dye ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhalle neuer haue other but oonly hym that I haue dyſcryuyd / to whome I ſhall truely kepe al the pure loue of my herte. And with this ſhe ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe vp / and hir moder &amp; all the lordes frome the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. And with great ſorowe / and lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacien they toke ther leue &amp; went on their way. &amp; thanne they yonge lady went home vnto hir paleys whoſe herte was ſo ſet on fyre with thys huſbonde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe had diſcryued that ſhe coude no thinge thynke n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> do but all hir mynde &amp; hir intencyon was only on hym / wherfoore ſhe ſtodyed &amp; muſed contynually howe ſhe myght fynde hym but it wold nat be as yit / forſoth ſhe had no meanes therto. Nat wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge he was full nere hir herte. for he it was that had kynled hir herte wyth a bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge fyres loue that ſhulde neuer be quenched by no peynene tribulacion which was wele ſene in hir glorio<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> paſſion herafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:24816:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 153 -->
                  <pb facs="tcp:24816:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 153 -->
Ere I leue this yonge quene as for a tyme ſyttyng in hir palyce co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually thinking and ymagynynge howe ſhe myght fynde this newe ſpouſe with many a tere of elongacyon and many a ſore ſyghe / for hir blynde ignoraunce and nowe I ſhall turne as our lorde wyl gyue me grace to ſhe we howe oure lorde by hys ſpeciall my racle clepyd hir to baptyme / in a ſynguler manere <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat neuer was herd of before ne ſith &amp; after howe <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e wedded hir viſibly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a glorious maner / ſhewi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hir ſoueraigne tokens of loue / that neuer was ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wid to none exthly creature ſaue only to oure lady his bleſſyd moder. ¶ Beſyde Alyſander a certeyn ſpace of myles ther dwelte an holy fader in deſerte that hight Adrian the which had ſerued oure holy fader almyghty god the ſpace of. xxx. yere in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te penaunce. And on a daye as he walked by foore his celle in meditacion / ther cam agaynſt hym the moſt reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lady that any erthly creature myght beholde. and whan the heremyte bihelde hir moſt excellent eſtate / and hyghe beaute aboue kynde he was ſo ſore aſtoned and dredefull that he fyl dow ne as deede. Thanne this bleſſyd lady ſeynge hys great drede / cleped him goodly by his name &amp; ſaid broder Adryan drede ye not for I am not come to you but for your great worſhyp honour &amp; profyte with that ſhe toke hym by the hand myldly &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted hym &amp; ſaide to hym in this wiſe. Adrian ye muſt go on a meſſage to the cyte of Aliſaundre for
<pb facs="tcp:24816:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 164 -->
                  <pb facs="tcp:24816:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 164 -->me and into the palys of the yonge Quene &amp; ther, ye muſt ſay to hir that that lady gretethe hyr well whoſe ſon ſhe chaſe to hir lorde and huſbonde ſyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge in hir parlement with hir moder and all hyr lordes aboute hir where ſhe had a greate contluy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and batayle in kepinge of hir virgynyte / and tel hir that the ſame lorde that ſhe dyd cheſe there ys my ſon that am a clene virgyn and he deſyreth hir beautye and he loueth hir chaſtite amonge all vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyns in erthe / &amp; byd hir without tariynge that ſhe come with you alone into this place and ſhe ſhalbe newe clothed and than ſhe ſhall ſee hym / and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue hym to hir euerlaſtinge ſpouſe. The heremyte heringe all this / anſwered thus. O bleſſed Lady howe ſhulde I do this meſſage. for nouther I kn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owe the cite ne the wey and what am I though I knewe it for to doo ſuche a meſſage vnto the quene Hir meny woll nat ſuffre me to come vnto hir pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence: and ſhe woll nat byleue me of my meſſage. but put me in duraunce as thoughe I were a fay. toure. ¶ Adryan ſaide this bleſſyd Lady drede ye nat for that that my ſon hath begonne in hir muſt nedis be perfourmed: for were ye well ſhe is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall choſyn veſſel of grace before all other women wherfore tary nat ne drede nat. For bothe ye ſhall knowe the cyte and alſo the wey into hyr Paleys for there ſhall no creature take hede to you.</p>
               <p>¶ And whan ye come into hir paleys take goode hede whiche dores open agaynſt you / and enter in
<pb facs="tcp:24816:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 155 -->
                  <pb facs="tcp:24816:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 155 -->boldly tyll that ye come vnto this faire yonge que ne whome ye ſhall fynde alone in hir ſtodye ſtody inge full ſore in hir wittis of that that woll nat be wherfore my ſon hath compaſſyon on hir laboure and for hir goode wyll ſhe ſhal be ſpecially fed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his grace that was neuer none lyke to hir / out ake myn owne ꝑſone that am his owne moder. wher fore Adryan hye you faſt &amp; bringe me my dere dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghter that I loue with all myn herte. And whan Adryan had receyued hys meſſage / he layde hym downe flatte before hys ſouerayne lady ſaynge in this wyſe. All worſhyp &amp; Ioy be to my lorde god your bleſſyd ſon. &amp; your bleſſyd wyll be fulfylled &amp; I woll go at your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The vii. chapter.</head>
               <p>And anone adrian roſe him vp &amp; hied him faſt to the cyte of aliſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der &amp; paſſed the deſert and ſo furth tyll he came to the cyte / and ſoo he wente furth to the paleys as he had lerned ſo dyd he / and entred in at the dores the whyche opened ageynſte hym / &amp; ſo he yode from chamber to chaumber tyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he cam to the ſecrete ſtody where as no creature vſed to come but ſhe hir ſelf alone / &amp; whan that he entred in at the dore he ſawe where ſate the faireſt creature &amp; the moſt goodly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any creature myght beholde / and ſhe ſate ſo ſadde in hir ſtody that ſhe herde hym nat vnto the tyme that he kneled hym</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
